A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
- Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009), Extent: 90434 emails.
  - Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries B. Lawrence Roberts, 2006-2010.
    This subseries contains 34247 emails in three PST files: LRoberts1.pst, LRoberts2.pst, and LRoberts3.pst. Lawrence Roberts served as Counselor to the Governor from 14 January 2006 until 9 March 2009 when resigned to take a position as Senior Advisor to the Chairman of the Democratic National Committee (Governor Tim Kaine). During the Kaine Administration, the Counselor to the Governor provided legal advice to the Governor, including liaison with the judiciary and the Office of the Attorney General. The Counselor also handled Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests, conflict of interest statements, contracts/leases for the Governor, settlement agreements for the Governor, clemency requests, death warrants, and provided broader advice to the Governor on political and personal matters as assigned. The Counselor was the chief liaison with the Democratic Party, the Moving Virginia Forward PAC, and outside political constituency groups. As part of his outreach efforts, the Counselor developed strategies to interact and facilitate implementation of the Governor's agenda. Roberts also worked with the Scheduling Director to oversee the Governor's time. After his resignation, Roberts continued to serve as an unpaid advisor to the Governor on four issues: the Commonwealth's response to the Virginia Tech tragedy; concluding clemency matters which he had worked on; reviewing his files and documents for archiving; and reaching an agreement with the Library of Virginia as to archiving policies as they apply to the Counselor to the Governor and his staff.
    - LRoberts1.pst, January 2006-January 2010.
      The LRoberts1.pst file contains 28542 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010. There are 8655 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, mediation and settlement discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information.
      Subjects include: 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including creation and report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, notes from meeting with family members, settlement agreements between Commonwealth and families and correspondence between Roberts and family members; revenue budget issues; transportation (drafts of June 2008 General Assembly special session speech, 2008 Kaine Transportation Plan, Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute, Tyson Tunnel Plan and Full Funding Grant Agreement (FFGA), 2007 abusive driver fees, Elliston intermodal facility in Montgomery County, 2006 General Assembly special session on transportation, and Coalfields Expressway); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007, 2008 and 2009); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2006, August 2007, December 2007 and August 2008); clemency (Edward Bell, Mario Bustillo, Christopher Scott Emmett, Kevin Green, Brandon Wayne Hedrick, Kent Jackson, Michael William Lenz, Norfolk Four, John Yancey Schmitt, Jens Soering, Dexter Lee Vinson, Percy Walton, Earl Washington and Robert Stacy Yarbrough-all restricted); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); open carry (firearms in state parks); archiving/records retention schedule for the Office of the Governor; talking points for February 2009 Virginia Congressional Delegation meeting (drafts); smoking ban in restaurants; proposal by the United States Navy to move a nuclear-powered aircraft carrier from Norfolk Naval Station to Naval Station Mayport, Florida; state government printing expenses (Freedom of Information Act request from Delegate Scott Lingamfelter); preparations for the 4 November 2008 presidential election; student voting; teleworking; Civil Rights Memorial; drafts of press releases/comments on media stories; Dominion Power's Wise County project; cabinet meetings (agendas); legislation/legislative sessions; Virginia Latino Advisory Board; election issues in Chesterfield County, 2008 Presidential primary; talking points (drafts, etc.) on a variety of subjects; resignation of Dr. Esam Omeish from Virginia Commission on Immigration; education (Pre-K, Start Strong); death of Oliver Hill and viewing at Governor's Mansion; Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood; judicial vacancies; personnel changes in Office of the Governor (esp. spring/summer 2007); health care work group; Governor incapacity and succession; Virginia tribal recognition; electricity re-regulation; Fort Monroe; Mirant Potomac River Generating Plant (Mirant Plant) in Alexandria; State Board of Elections issues; agreements with Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE)/287(g) [Executive Work Group related to possible state immigration authority with ICE under 287 (g) (8 USC Section 1357 (g))]; Comprehensive Services Act (CSA); Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA)/Arlington; energy policy; drafts of some executive orders; Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach; Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM); Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); 2006 budget impasse; menhaden fisheries management measures; rejection by General Assembly of Danny LeBlanc, Kaine's selection for Secretary of the Commonwealth and successful confirmation of Kate Hanley for same post; DNA testing/old DFS files; domestic partner benefits; Employee Free Choice Act; estate tax repeal; TANF (Temporary Assistance for Needy Families); and Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman (VITA/NG).
      Notable email: email from Tim Kaine, 15 October 2007, Budget Issues I Care About; email from Mark Rubin on Supreme Court roll out of Judge Goodwyn, 3 October 2007; email from Kaine on improving vetting process after resignation of Dr. Esam Omeish, 27 September 2007; Kaine's comments on speech to money committees (18 August 2007); email thread started by Kaine on the operations/structure of the Governor's Office (3 April 2007); email from Kaine on electricity reregulation (17 March 2007); emails from Kaine on transportation (22 July 2008, 1 July 2008, 9 May 2008, 8 May 2008, 28 April 2008, 19 March 2008, 2 April 2007, 30 March 2007, 20 March 2007, 28 February 2007, 5 February 2007); email threads on abusive driver fees (19 July 2007, 18 July 2007, 17 July 2007, 16 July 2007); email from Larry Roberts, 7 May 2007, on strategic scheduling for 2007; email from Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage, 4 May 2007, on budget time line/schedule; email thread between Roberts and Turnage, 26 April 2007, about hiring Suzette Denslow as Deputy Policy Director and Leighty's unhappiness; email from Ric Signer to Leighty (Roberts cc'd), 17 April 2007, on the trade mission to Japan; email thread on electric reregulation (see Kaine's lengthy email dated 17 March 2007).
      Correspondents include: James Alcorn, Amber Amato, Viola Baskerville, Tim Bass, Sindy Benavides, Mark Bowles, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Kim Busch, Larry Byrne, Aneesh Chopra, Clyde Cristman, Robert Crouch, Barnie Day, Suzette Denslow, Nick Donohue, Jason Eige, Kim Farrar, Patrick Finnerty, Marc Follmer, Manju Ganeriwala, Cathy Ghidotti, Kathy Glazer, Patrick Gottschalk, Eric Gregory (assistant AG), Kevin Hall, Kate Hanley, Stephen Harms, Sherrie Harrington, Bernard Henderson, Maurcie Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Pierce Homer, Gail Jaspen, Jean Jensen, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent (assistant AG), Jeff Kraus, Danny LeBlanc, Keetch leGrand, William Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, John Marshall, Maureen Matsen (assistant AG), Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Bill Murray, Thomas Nesbitt (assistant AG), Steve Owens (assistant AG), Kate Paris, David Paylor, Sarah Plumb, Barbara Reese, Nancy Rodrigues, Nikki Rovener, Mark Rubin, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Brian Sheppard, Ric Siger, Williams Sims, Delacey Skinner, D.B. Smit, Jeff Southard, Phil Sunderland, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Matthew Tucker, Wayne Turnage, Jim Ukrop, Jody Wagner, Stephen Walz, Tom Whipple, and Richard Zorn.
    - LRoberts2.pst, 2006-2010.
      The LRoberts2.pst file contains 288 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010. Subjects include: American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); Federal issues impacting Virginia; and Virginia tribal recognition.
      Correspondents include: Gena Boyle, Eileen Filler-Corn, William Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Barbara Reese, and Brian Sheppard.
    - LRoberts3.pst, 2006-2010.
      The LRoberts3.pst file contains 5417 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010. There are 4033 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, mediation and settlement discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information.
      Subjects include: 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including leak of report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel to the New York Times; email thread between Chief of Staff Bill Leighty and Secretary of Natural Resources Preston Bryant, 16 May 2007, in which Leighty discusses how he informed Governor Kaine about the Virginia Tech shooting; retirement of Chief of Staff William H. Leighty in 2007; archiving/records retention schedule for the Office of the Governor; personnel changes in Office of the Governor (esp. spring/summer 2007); DNA testing/old DFS files; drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007, 2008 and 2009); preparations for the 4 November 2008 presidential election; drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly ( August 2007, December 2007); transportation (Tysons Corner tunnel, 2007 legislation, abusive driver fees); Clemency; Maurice Henderson, Deputy Press Secretary, reports from 2006-2007 press gaggles/news conferences; drafts of Kaine's 2006 commencement address at the University of Virginia; rejection by General Assembly of Danny LeBlanc, Kaine's selection for Secretary of the Commonwealth; and clemency (Edward Bell, Mario Bustillo, Christopher Scott Emmett, Kevin Green, Brandon Wayne Hedrick, Kent Jackson, Michael William Lenz, Norfolk Four, John Yancey Schmitt, Jens Soering, Dexter Lee Vinson, Percy Walton, Earl Washington and Robert Stacy Yarbrough-all restricted).
      Notable email: email from Kaine, 23 April 2007, describing the policy development agenda for the rest of 2007; email thread between Roberts and Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage, 26 April 2007, about hiring Suzette Denslow as Deputy Policy Director and Leighty's unhappiness; email thread between Turnage and Roberts, 27 April 2007, discussing issues with Leighty; email exchange between Roberts and Sherrie Harrington, 9 November 2006, re: execution of John Yancey Schmitt; email exchange between Roberts and Turnage, 7 June and 9 June 2006 on scheduled execution of Percy Walton; email from Marilyn Tavenner, 5 June 2006, on scheduled execution of Percy Walton; email exchange between Roberts and Brian Sheppard, 27 April 2006, re: execution of Dexter Lee Vinson; and email thread between Kaine, Roberts and Delacey Skinner, 17 April and 16 April 2006, on Kaine's concerns about the marriage amendment.
      Correspondents include: Amber Amato, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Katherine Burnett, Aneesh Chopra, Clyde Cristman, Marla Decker, Shane Emmett, Helen Fahey, Cathy Ghidotti, Patrick Gottschalk, Kevin Hall, Robert Hall, Sherrie Harrington, Bernard Henderson, Maurice Henderson, II, E. Desmond Hogan, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent, Danny LeBlanc, William Leighty, John Marshall, Walter McFarlane, William Mims, Jeff Mitchell, Bill Murray, Thomas Nesbitt, Sarah Plumb, Brian Pumphrey, Mark Rubin, Brian Sheppard, Delacey Skinner, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, and Wayne Turnage.
  - Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries C. Mark Rubin Email, 2006-2010.
    This subseries contains 10262 emails in two PST files: KaineLibmrubin.pst and MRUBIN.pst. Mark Rubin served as Deputy Counselor and Senior Advisor to the Governor from 14 January 2006 to 9 March 2009. Following the resignation of Lawrence Roberts, Rubin served as Counselor to the Governor from 10 March 2009 to 16 January 2010. The Senior Advisor was a hybrid position. He provided legal assistance to the Counselor and legislative assistance to the Policy Director. The Senior Advisor as helped mediate important policy disputes for the Governor. Rubin frequently met with legislators and others and shared what he learned with senior administration officials. His email provides information on legislation development and the legislative process.
    - KaineLibmrubin.pst, 2006-2010.
      The KaineLibmrubin.pst file contains 10260 emails sent and received by Mark Rubin between January 2006 and January 2010. There are 1563 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, mediation and settlement discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.
      Subjects include: 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including issues regarding the settlement agreements between Commonwealth and families, forwarded emails sent to families by Jay Poole, Director of Virginia Tech's Office of Recovery and Support, and correspondence between Rubin and family members; budget issues including fall 2009 state agency reduction plans; legislation; transportation (2008 Kaine Transportation Plan, 2007 abusive driver fees, and 2006 General Assembly special session on transportation); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007 and 2009); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (December 2007, August 2008, December 2009); blanket restoration of rights; closure of Natural Bridge Juvenile Correctional Center; Virginia's response to the Melendez-Diaz v. Massachusetts, 557 U.S. 205 (2009), United States Supreme Court decision that ruled that it was a violation of the Sixth Amendment right of confrontation for a prosecutor to submit lab testing results without the testimony of the person who performed the test; Virginia tribal recognition; smoking ban in restaurants; payday lending; Dominion Power's Wise County project; eminent domain; uranium mining; mental health legislation; work group for the Virginia Birth-Related Neurological Injury Compensation Program; Education (Pre-K); Mirant Potomac River Generating Plant (Mirant Plant) in Alexandria; energy policy (including Renewable Portfolio Standards); electricity re-regulation; indigent defense; machinery and tools legislation; Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); setting dates for special elections; clemency (Jens Soering, John T. Harrison, Daniel Cox, Richard M. Hawkins, Chris Sharikas, Joseph Giarrantano, Larry Bill Elliott, Whitney Shelton, Norfolk Four, and Earl Washington-all restricted); and Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach.
      Notable email: email thread between Tim Kaine and Mark Rubin, 16 April 2008, relaying a conversation Kaine had with Delegate David Alba on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 18 April 2008, to Mark Rubin, Larry Roberts, Suzette Denslow, Brian Shepard, Pierce Homer and Delacey Skinner, relaying a conversation Kaine had with Delegate Joe May on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 8 May 2008, to Mark Rubin, Larry Roberts, Suzette Denslow, Brian Shepard, Pierce Homer and Delacey Skinner, relaying a conversation Kaine had with several legislators on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 17 March 2007, to Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Larry Roberts, Patrick Gottschalk, Preston Bryant, and Bill Leighty, listing his concerns with the electric reregulation bill; email from Tim Kaine, 30 May 2006, to Larry Roberts, Jody Wagner, and Mark Rubin, sharing additional thoughts on the budget; email thread between Tim Kaine and Mark Rubin, 28 April 2008, setting the process for selection of circuit court judges, Supreme Court and an SCC judge; email from Mark Rubin, 11 February 2006, to Larry Roberts, Bill Leighty, Brian Shepard, Preston Bryant, Mike Henry, Bill Murray, and Daniel LeBlanc, detailing the latest vote count in the General Assembly to confirm LeBlanc as Secretary of the Commonwealth; email from Preston Bryant, 12 February 2006, to Mark Rubin, describing his conversations with several members of the House of Delegates on the LeBlanc nomination; email from Tim Kaine, 8 August 2006, to Bill Murray, Bill Leighty, Brian Shepard, and Mark Rubin, with Kaine's notes from phone conversations with several members of the General Assembly (notes as attachment) on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 15 August 2006, 17 August 2006, and 21 August 2006, to Mark Rubin, Bill Murray and Brian Shepard, describing Kaine's contacts with several members of the General Assembly on transportation; email from Mark Rubin, 23 April 2006, to Brian Shepard and Bill Murray, on post mortem on the 2006 General Assembly session; email from Tim Kaine, 27 November 2009, to Wayne Turnage, Stephen Harms, and Ric Brown, where Kaine shares his views on eliminating the car tax in his final budget; and email from Tim Kaine, 6 February 2008, to Jody Wagner, Ric Brown, Wayne Turnage, Stephen Harms, Brian Shepard, Mark Rubin, Suzette Denslow, Larry Roberts, Delacey Skinner, and Gordon Hickey, in which Kaine shares his thoughts on the budget.
      Correspondents include: Philip Abraham, Amber Amato, David Bailey, Chris Bast, Steve Benjamin, Robert Blue, Gena Boyle, William Broaddus, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Don Carr, Bob Chase, Marc Cheatham, Eileen Filler-Corn, Robert Crouch, Marla Decker, George Deebo, Suzette Denslow, Chip Dicks, Dave Dickson, Betsy Edwards, Jerry Edwards, Mike Edwards, Shane Emmett, Helen Fahey, Claudia Farr, Frank Ferguson, Marc Follmer, May Fox, Robert Hall, Stephanie Hamlett, Stephen Harms, Kay Heidbreder, Bernard Henderson, Pierce Homer, Barbara Hulburt, Gail Jaspen, Jean Jensen, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent, Anne Leigh Kerr, Jim Kibler, Irene Leech, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Maureen Matsen, Michael Maul, Walter McFarlane, Bill McKelway, Eric Murdock, Bill Murray, Stephen Parker, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Nancy Rodrigues, Michele Satterlund, Aimee Perron Seibert, Brian Shepard, Ric Signer, Jeff Southard, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Wayne Turnage, Bret Vassey, Jody Wagner, Stephen Walz, and Kent Willis.
    - MRUBIN.pst, 2010.
      The MRUBIN.pst file contains two email messages received by Mark Rubin dated 15 January 2010. One message is from Kent Willis of the Virginia American Civil Liberties Union on Kaine's decision not to issue a blanket restoration of rights executive order. The second message is from Gordon Hickey regarding Jens Soering.
  - Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries D. Shane Emmett Email, 2008-2010.
    This subseries contains 1090 emails in one PST file: KaineLibsemmett.pst. Shane Emmett worked as a Governor's Legal Fellow and as a Deputy Counselor to Mark Rubin from December 2008 to January 2010.
    The KaineLibsemmett.pst contains 1090 email messages sent and received by Shane Emmett. There are 980 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: pardon and restoration of rights records.
    Subjects include: clemency (Edward Bell, Norfolk Four, Joseph Giarrantano, Larry Bill Elliott, Jens Soering, and John Muhammad-all restricted); and domestic partner benefits.
    Correspondents include: Katherine Burnett Baldwin, Andrew Block, Klaus Botzet, Marla Decker, Helen Fahey, E. Desmond Hogan, Gail Jaspen, Tim Kaine, Tom Kelly, Walter McFarlane, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, and Donald Salzman.
  - Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries E. William H. Leighty Email, 2002-2007.
    This subseries contains 15893 emails in one PST file: Leighty.pst. William H. Leighty served as Chief of Staff to Governor Mark R. Warner (January 2002-January 2006). He was reappointed Chief of Staff by Governor Tim Kaine. On 23 May 2007 Leighty announced his retirement effective 1 September 2007. He stepped down as Chief of Staff effective 25 May 2007. Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage assumed his duties. Leighty remained in the administration as Chief Emeritus working on several projects including efforts to improve minority procurement for state agencies, workforce development and the implementation of the out sourcing of state governments' IT functions. The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government for all aspects of service to citizens. The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office. Governors Mark Warner and Tim Kaine delegated additional responsibilities to Leighty in Executive Order 3 (2002) Authority and Responsibility of Chief of Staff and Executive Order 4 (2006) Authority and Responsibility of Chief of Staff.
    The Leighty.pst file contains 15893 email messages sent and received by William H. Leighty between January 2002 and September 2007. There are 141 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: investigative records, attorney-client privileged documents, and medical information.